Coding has been
the bread and butter for
developers since
the dawn of computing.
We're used to creating
applications by breaking down
requirements into
composable problems
that can then be coded against.
So for example, if
we have to write
an application that figures
out a stock analytic,
maybe the price
divided by the ratio,
we can usually write code to get
the values from a data source,
do the calculation and
then return the result.
Or if we're writing a game
we can usually figure
out the rules.
For example, if the ball hits
the brick then the brick should
vanish and the ball
should rebound.
But if the ball falls
off the bottom of
the screen then maybe
the player loses their life.
We can represent that
with this diagram.
Rules and data go in
answers come out.
Rules are expressed in
a programming language
and data can come from
a variety of sources from
local variables all the
way up to databases.
Machine learning
rearranges this diagram
where we put answers in data
in and then we get rules out.
So instead of us as
developers figuring
out the rules when should
the brick be removed,
when should
the player's life end,
or what's the desired analytic
for any other concept,
what we will do is we
can get a bunch of
examples for what we want to
see and then have the computer
figure out the rules.
Now, this is particularly
valuable for problems that
you can't solve by figuring
the rules out for yourself.
So consider this example,
activity recognition.
If I'm building a device that
detects if somebody is say
walking and I have data
about their speed,
I might write code like this
and if they're
running well that's
a faster speed so I
could adapt my code
to this and if they're biking,
well that's not too bad either.
I can adapt my code like this.
But then I have to do
golf recognition too,
now my concept becomes broken.
But not only that,
doing it by speed alone
of course is quite naive.
We walk and run at
different speeds uphill and
downhill and other people
walk and run at
different speeds to us.
So, let's go back
to this diagram.
Ultimately machine
learning is very
similar but we're just
flipping the axes.
So instead of me trying
to express the problem as
rules when often that
isn't even possible,
I'll have to compromise.
The new paradigm is that I get
lots and lots of
examples and then I have
labels on those
examples and I use
the data to say this is
what walking looks like,
this is what running looks like,
this is what biking
looks like and yes,
even this is what
golfing looks like.
So, then it becomes
answers and data
in with rules being
inferred by the machine.
A machine learning algorithm then
figures out the
specific patterns in
each set of data that
determines the
distinctiveness of each.
That's what's so powerful and
exciting about
this programming paradigm.
It's more than just a new way
of doing the same old thing.
It opens up new possibilities
that were infeasible
to do before.
So in the next few minutes,
I'm going to show you
the basics of creating
a neural network which is
the workhorse of doing this type
of pattern recognition.
A neural network is
just a slightly more
advanced implementation of
machine learning and we
call that deep learning.
But fortunately it's
actually very easy to code.
So, we're just going to jump
straight into deep learning.
We'll start with a simple one
and then we'll move on
to one that does computer vision
in about 10 lines of code.
But let's start with a very
simple "Hello World" example.
So you can see just how
everything hangs together.